www.linkedin.com/in/nirmalkn nirmal.kanagasabai@mail.mcgill.ca Mob: (+1) 514 803 5633

SUMMARY

First Year Graduate Student at the School of Computer Science, McGill University with 22 months of work experience as a Java programmer and Web Application developer. Solid academic training in Design Patterns, Object-Oriented Analysis and Design and Databases.

EDUCATION

Sept 2016	M.Sc. Computer Science (Thesis)	
- Present	McGill University, Montreal, Canada	
	Master's Thesis: 'Modelling in the Cloud' under Prof. Joerg Kienzle	
2010 - 2014	Bachelor of Technology: Information Technology	9.23 (out of 10)
	Pondicherry Engineering College, Puducherry, India	Gold Medalist

WORK EXPERIENCE

Sept 2016 - Present	Graduate Research Assistant – Software Engineering Lab McGill University, Montreal, Canada	
Sept 2016 - Present	Teaching Assistant – (Software Engineering Project) McGill University, Montreal, Canada	1 yr course
Oct 2014 - Jul 2016	Systems Engineer - Infosys Ltd Mahindra City, Chennai, India	1.83 years

Jul 2016	Mahindra City, Chennai, India			
AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS				
2015	Government of Puducherry Prize For securing 1 st rank in the University examination held during the period of the B. Tech. course, conducted by Pondicherry University			
2010 - 2014	Proficiency (Academics) Topper (Rank 1) on all four years consecutively out of a batch of 72 students			
Apr 2014	TCS Best Student Award – Tata Consultancy Services, India Adjudged for the academic excellence for the academic years 2010 - 2014			
Apr 2014	Mr. Amrita Memorial Award - Best All Rounder Awarded for meritorious performance in both co-curricular and extra-curricular activities			
Feb 2013	Best Paper Award - National Conference on Bio-Inspired Science and Technology Conferred for a paper published on 'Forensic Fingerprint Enhancement through Morphological Image Processing' for its complexity and diverse use of applications			
Feb 2013	2 nd Prize (Paper Presentation) For presenting an extensive survey paper on 'Polarization Imaging Based Outdoor Water Detection' at the technical fest with over 300 participants.			
Dec 2012	1 st Prize (Paper Presentation) Secured 1 st Prize for presenting a widespread analysis on 'Morphological Image Processing' at the technical fest organized by SJS Pauls Engineering College, Puducherry			

GRADUATE THESIS

Working on my thesis titled, 'Modelling in Cloud' under Prof. Joerg Kienzle. It primarily involves development of a cloud repository to store the reusable concerns and introduce collaborative modelling to the large scale agile concern-oriented software modelling tool 'TouchCORE'.

TECHNICAL EXPERTISE

Languages/Technologies C, C++, Java, J2EE, JSF, Hibernate 3.0, SQL, HTML, JPA

Scripting Languages Python (Beginner), JavaScript
Databases Oracle 11g, MongoDB (Beginner)

WORK EXPERIENCE (at Infosys Ltd)

Role: J2EE Developer Client: Royal Bank of Scotland Domain: Financial Services

Responsibilities:

- Client Interaction, requirements gathering and elicitation
- Creation of design prototypes
- Implementation using MVC Architectural pattern: JSF, Spring, Hibernate and Oracle
- Responsible for problem, incident and change management for production bugs

PUBLICATIONS

Apr 2014	An efficient algorithm for fast block motion estimation in High Efficiency Video Coding 4 th IEEE International Conference on Recent Trends in IT (ICRTIT 2014)
Feb 2014	Enhancements of Latent Fingerprints using Morphological Filters International Journal of Engineering Research and Technology ISSN 2278-0181
Dec 2013	Spam Termination and Establishing Private Search Logs Second National Conference on Information Technology (NCIT 2013)
Feb 2013	Forensic Fingerprint Enhancement through Morphological Image Processing National Conference on Bio-inspired Systems and Technologies (NCBST '13)

UNDERGRADUATE THESIS

An Efficient Algorithm for Fast Block Motion Estimation in High Efficiency Video Coding

The algorithm involves a direction-based approach on several distinctly identified combinations of search points. Five different schemes were introduced based on the combinations of search points and were experimented on several standard video sequences to predict the motion vector of the candidate block.

UNDERGRADUATE PROJECT

NIMBUS Drive – File Deduplication using Genetic Programming for Efficient Cloud Storage

The objective is to provide an optimal solution to the problem encountered in cloud storage space posed by the presence of duplicates. Syntactic text comparison and Genetic Programming were used to detect the closest match.

OTHER ACADEMIC PROJECTS

•	Predict Marathon Winner (Machine Learning)	Python, R
•	Singleton Approaches (Modelling)	Models & Java
•	Nimbus Drive (Unisys Cloud 20/20 V5)	J2EE, JavaScript + AJAX
•	Employee Record Management (DIET, Pdy)	Visual Basic 6.0
•	Designed seven websites	HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript

WORKSHOPS

- Research Issues and Challenges in SE
- Hadoop
- NoSQL

- Employability Skills
- Oracle
- Image Processing Techniques